Here's my conspiracy. Eiffel 65, wanting
to reclaim the former glory of their hit
song Blue Daba, created a marketing
campaign all the way back in the late
1800s when Methylene Blue was first
invented and started influencing people
to start dropping blue liquid into their
drinks. What do you think? Is it more or
less believable than some of the other
conspiracy theories out there? I
actually wasn't exaggerating when I
mentioned that methylene blue was
invented in the 1800s, but it was used
as a synthetic dye in the textile
industry, not as a marketing campaign by
a 1990s band. Of late, methylene blue
has been gaining popularity for its
supposed health benefits. And that's
what I'd like to get into because wow,
are there claims, but few people
actually open the studies to see what
scientists have to say. So, how about
it? In this study, researchers wanted to
find out what happens to the brains of
people given methylene blue or a
placebo, a blue food coloring dye. So,
they performed cognitive tests,
including scans, on these participants
before being given either treatment and
then consumed the treatments before
doing some puzzles and some other
cognitive tasks, then did another brain
scan and some more tests. Aside from
this acute study, they also followed up
one week later. The idea behind
methylene blue comes down to an
admittedly fascinating mechanism. I've
covered this in the past, but the
primary mechanism of methylene blue to
us is that it's an electron
cyclinger. And since 99% of people don't
know what that is, I'll explain. Inside
the mitochondria of your
cells, yes, the powerhouse of the cell
is this complex of proteins called the
electron transport chain. That chain of
proteins exchanges electrons to allow
mitochondrian to generate ATP, cellular
energy. I'm not going to go too into
proton pumping and the mode of force.
But all you need to know is that the
exchange of electrons allows cellular
energy in the form of ATP to be
generated. Great. Without it, we die.
Okay. Now, one of the major problems
with this chain of proteins that move
electrons is the fact that the electrons
can also slip off the chain and interact
with nearby molecules, creating
unstable, damaging molecules called
reactive oxygen species. These molecules
ROS can interact with components of our
mitochondria and even the rest of our
cells and cause damage. Here is where
methylene blue comes in. Methylene blue
can act as an electron acceptor thereby
reducing the electrons aberrantly
interacting with other molecules and
forming these damaging molecules. Beyond
that though and even cooler it can
donate the electron back to the correct
proteins especially complex 4 further
along the complex of proteins there. In
doing so, it not only reduces oxidative
stress from these damaging molecules,
but it also facilitates some energy
production that wouldn't otherwise have
been possible through this lost
electron. Methylene blue has other
effects like those described in this
review, like its effects on serotonin or
its interaction on a few different
enzymes in our cells, but the main one
discussed is mitochondrial. The actions
of methylene blue are very context
dependent as we'll get into. First,
let's discuss what the researchers
discovered. Here we go. As you can
clearly see, methylene blue had
tremendous Oh, you have no idea how to
read this. Well, don't feel bad because
I had no idea either. So, upon some
research on the research, second order
research inception, it's much simpler
than I thought. We're looking at a bold
functional MRI scan. It's called bold
because it's measuring blood flow as a
metric of brain activity. So bold for
blood
oxygenate bold for blood oxygen level
dependent MRI. The less oxygen, the
greater the brain activity. The reason
behind that is that this measures
deoxxygenated hemoglobin found in your
red blood cells. Your red blood cells
have proteins inside of them called
hemoglobin that have a strong attraction
to oxygen like I do for motorcycles. And
when oxygen is delivered from the red
blood cell to the brain tissue,
hemoglobin gets deoxxygenated. Meaning
that the oxygen is taken away and sent
to the tissue. That means that the
neural or brain cell has it, which would
imply neural activity as there's need
for oxygen. So the images here indicate
by varying color the level of
statistically significant difference
between the brain of the placeboc
consuming individuals and the methylene
blue consuming individuals. If there's a
color that means there's a greater
deoxxygenation or a greater brain
activity in that region when using
methylene blue. We can clearly see if we
squint multiple areas where bold
activity is greater with methylene blue.
Oh, the bottom half of the figure is
simply different tests that the
participants had to do. It doesn't
inform us on the actual differences
between the groups. Now, as fun as it is
to look at changes in blood flow, we're
more interested in actual outcomes. Is
your brain functioning better? Well,
let's look. We have the baseline results
on the left and the post treatment
results on the right. The methylene blue
or MB condition there clearly shows an
improvement in correct responses to a
cognitive test. while the placebo does
not show these improvements. If you're
wondering if there were any baseline
differences since it looks like there's
a difference before, uh there's
apparently no statistically identified
difference. I find that hard to believe,
but I have to go with what the
statistics show. So no difference at
baseline and even no difference between
the groups afterward, but there is a
difference within group when only
comparing baseline to after in the
methylene blue. Exactly how you can have
a sixpoint difference with such a small
error bars and no between groups effect
is honestly beyond me, but I report what
the researchers mention. Either way,
this offers evidence that methylene blue
improves brain function. I should also
mention that the longer term results
offered no such benefit that but that
might be because of the testing was
pretty lackluster. It was done over
email. I wouldn't consider that very
sound practice for controlling for
possible variables like I don't know a
screaming child having to run to work.
Uh the infinite life circumstances that
could screw up testing especially in
such a small sample size. Okay, but this
is uh one study and there have been
others and there's also some caution
related to dosing of methylene blue. So,
let's get into that right after I
mention that I'll be discussing this
more in live sessions with my insider
community. If you're interested in
covering methylene blue in more depth
along with getting access to all my
work, private podcasts, uh more videos,
a premium email list that delivers
actionable takeaways to your inbox every
week, and much more. Consider checking
out the Physionic Insiders link is in
the description. Okay, dosing. The study
that we just went over used 4 milligs
per kilogram of weight to show effect.
However, in this review, the researchers
point out that low doses could be
effective while larger doses can be
detrimental. And as one example,
methylene blue is approved for the use
of to treat a condition
called
methamog
methomoglobinmia. Sometimes
pronunciation is half the battle. And
yet high doses of methylene blue are
known to cause the same condition. I'm
not repeating the name. This highlights
the importance of dose. Further, other
studies in methylene blue are focused on
dementia, but these studies come back
with mixed results with no benefit at
certain doses, although those doses are
very much in line with the study that we
just went over. So, we have several
mechanistic studies that indicate its
effectiveness as well as its harm at
higher doses. We have this human trial
that we went over that indicates
benefit. And we have some dementia
trials indicating benefit and others
indicating no benefit. If I65 wants to
make their song popular again, they may
have to try something a bit more potent
or hope that this stuff actually turns
people blue. In fact, that's exactly
what's happening. This is a real picture
of methylene blue on the brain. So maybe
that is the plan. Slowly turning into a
blue world. Actually, this is a direct
quote from the song. Listen up. Here's a
story about a little guy that lives in a
blue world and all day and all night.
And everything he sees is just blue like
him inside and
outside. Blue is his house with a blue
little window and a blue Corvette. Now,
personally, I would go with a 918
Spider, but those weren't out then. And
everything is blue for him and himself
and everybody around. I mean, come on.
That conspiracy isn't sounding so
conspiracy anymore, is it? Just uh don't
think about the timetable of it all and
we can make this work. Anyway, yes, blue
tongues, blue brains, and so on make me
wonder if anyone that enjoys methylene
blue is also a hardcore it has to be
natural in other aspects of the life.
The the cognitive dissonance must be
thunderous inside that blue brain.
Anyway, what do we make of all this?
Well, the best case scenario is that
methylene blue mildly improves cognitive
performance. The more realistic scenario
is to say that methylene blue has
limited evidence on its brain efficacy
with a mixture of results. And
considering that there are more proven
cognitive enhancers and considering that
the uncertainty around dosing, it has
relatively weak evidence in support of
it being used at this time of this
recording. But if you're more interested
in methylene blue's longevity effects,
check this out. Otherwise, there's a
noniffle 65 related cognitive boosting
right here. Cue the music until I have
to take it down for copyright reasons.